<?xml version='1.0' encoding="utf-8"?>

<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 -->
<!-- or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; -->
<!-- with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. -->
<!-- A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU -->
<!-- Free Documentation License". -->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Engines</title>
  <para>
    You can add engines by activating the appropriate menu item within
    the "add" submenu of the "edit" menu item. You may change the properties
    of an engine by opening the properties dialog from the context menu at the
    top of each machine within vertical order. From the context menu you may
    perform some other tasks, as well.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The edit submenu is only available by sequencers like AgsDrum and AgsMatrix.
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To move up or down an engine open context menu and activate "up"
	respectively "down" entry.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To show or hide an engine open context menu and activate "show"
	respectively "hide" entry. Note the engines won't be hidden entirely
	they are just collapsed.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To rename an engine open context menu and activate "rename" entry.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To remove an engine open context menu and activate "destroy" entry.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	To open properties dialog open context menu and activate "properties"
	entry. There you might link, resize or asign LADSPA effects to channels.
	NOTE for LADSPA sink or generators aren't supported, yet.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	Edit gives you editing options.
      </para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  Copy pattern does convert your pattern bitmap into a pattern based notation suitable
	  to paste in notation editor.
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
	  
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect1>
    <title>Machine properties</title>
    <para>
      Within properties dialog you can link lines either in single channel or in bulk mode, add effects
      and adjust audio-channels/pads.
    </para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Output tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_machine_properties-output.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The machine properties dialog screenshot - output tab
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	The output tab lets you mainly perform linking lines and adding effects to them. For each
	line there's a combo box listing available linking engines, on the right of it there is
	a spin button let you choose the input line to be linked.
	As you have added a plugin by clicking add and selected appropriate effect by using plugin browser
	dialog. You may remove it by clicking checkbox of the listed plugin and finally click remove.
	Note you can have a effect only once per channel.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Input tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_machine_properties-input.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The machine properties dialog screenshot - input tab
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	The input tab does the mainly same as output tab in view of input lines. If supported
	you might assign files, too. In general you connect output to input.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Link input tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_machine_properties-link_input.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The machine properties dialog screenshot - link input tab
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	Do linking in batch mode. This means you're able to assign multiple lines at once.
	Thus you have to decide what start channel on each side to use and the count of
	lines to be linked.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Resize channels tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_machine_properties-resize_channels.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The machine properties dialog screenshot - resize tab
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	Adjust audio channels or input/output pads. If supported the GUI may provide more
	lines and pads as increasing the amount.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>LADSPA browser dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_ladspa_browser.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The LADSPA browser dialog screenshot
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	The plugin browser gives you choice of available LADSPA or Lv2 plugins. It lets you modify
	the controls to be used. The added plugin can be removed by activating checkbox in
	output/input tab and clicking remove.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Audio connection dialog</title>
    <para>
      The audio connection dialog allows you to specify to what soundcard to output. This can be
      modified either by assigning single channels or in bulk mode.
    </para>

    <sect2>
      <title></title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_audio_connection_output_line.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The audio connection output line screenshot
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
	Select the desired soundcard and don't forget to click enable. In order apply your modifications.
	After click OK.
      </para>    
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title></title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_audio_connection_bulk_line.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The audio connection output bulk screenshot
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
	The output connection tab allows you to link a bunch of channel at once.
      </para>    
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>MIDI dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_audio_connection_bulk_output.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The audio connection screenshot
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	The MIDI dialog allows you to select the MIDI sequencer to assign of the current machine.
	You might want to perform start and end key. Further you can adjust the start and end channel.
      </para>    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Panel</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="../images/ags_panel.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The panel screenshot
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      The panel is used for outputting to your soundcard and should be at topmost of your
      audio processing tree. It contains per audio channel a mute check box.
    </para>
    <para>
      Due the synchroneous nature of the output engine you're just able to adjust the audio
      channels. The output pads aren't visible and the ones available for input are packed
      vertically.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Mixer</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="../images/ags_mixer.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The mixer screenshot
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Bundle audio lines with the mixer and perform toplevel stream manipulation. It contains
      per audio channel a volume indicator and may contain LADSPA or Lv2 plugins.
    </para>
    <para>
      Due the limitation of recycling it is just able to handle multiple input lines and only one
      output pad. Whereas the output is hidden. They are locate just below the machine's menu tool
      button. 
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Drum</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="../images/ags_drum.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The drum screenshot
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Produce an audio stream by defining a pattern. The drum supports opening audio files and
      associate to its input. You might doing it by open button located preceeding to pattern
      box. Thus multi-selection of files is supported and assigning can be controlled by the
      controls just above the action widgets. The drum input pad contains an open button, too.
      It assigns available audio channels of the file to the grouped lines. One more way to
      assign audio files is doing it so by link editor of machine's property dialog.
      The drum may contain LADSPA plugins, too.
    </para>
    <para>
      The drum may contain multiple input as well output pads. They are packed on top of the
      composite widget, just below the machine's menu tool button. The input is packed horizontally
      followed by vertically packed output.
      The edit button within every input pad enables it as current input for editing pattern data.
      Further you may de-/activate the group toggle button to control audio channel assignment.
    </para>
    <para>
      Next to the multi-selection enable open button there's a loop check-box followed by the run
      button what starts the drum sequencer. It follows the into a two dimensional matrix packed
      pattern banks. Labeled from 1 to 12 and an the combined index labeled a throughout d. The
      length spin-button controls the number of pattern pads to be played in sequence which may
      be looped.
    </para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>The pattern box</title>
      <para>
	As entering to pattern box with focus the only way to get out of it is by tabulator key.
	With arrow keys you may navigate within pattern or toggle with space.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Left, Left-Arrow
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Move within pattern box left, as the pattern pad control is activate you get
		an audible feedback.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Right, Right-Arrow 
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Move within pattern box right, audible feedback as above.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Up, Up-Arrow
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Decrease pattern box offset about available number of pattern pads, audible feedback as above.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Down, Down-Arrow 
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Increase pattern box offset about available number of pattern pads, audible feedback as above.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Space
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Toggle audio pattern and give audible feedback.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Ctrl+c
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Copy the current pattern to clipboard
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Tab
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Leave pattern box focus.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Matrix</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="../images/ags_matrix.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The matrix screenshot
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Produce an audio stream by defining a pattern. The matrix itselves doesn't
      have any audio signals on its own input you may rather link it to a synth
      engine. The matrix is a rectangular area you may navigate within by arrow keys
      or toggle pattern by hiting space.
      The matrix is a true mono device but you may emulate multiple channels by doing
      multi-output. This is fulfilled by adjusting output pads within machine's properties
      dialog.
    </para>
    <para>
      Run button comes first and is followed by a one dimensional vector bank index
      labeled from 1 to 9. Then follows the matrix you have to leave it by hiting tab
      then you might modify sequence length or do loop control of the sequence.
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Left, Left-Arrow
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Move within matrix left, as the pattern pad control is activate you get
	      an audible feedback.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Right, Right-Arrow 
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Move within matrix right, audible feedback as above.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Up, Up-Arrow
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Decrease matrix offset about available number of pattern pads, audible feedback as above.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Down, Down-Arrow 
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Increase matrix offset about available number of pattern pads, audible feedback as above.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Space
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Toggle audio pattern and give audible feedback.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Ctrl+c
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Copy the current pattern to clipboard
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Tab
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Leave matrix focus.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Synth</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="../images/ags_synth.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The synth screenshot
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Produce audio data using its oscillators. The count of oscillators depends on number of
      input lines. They are adjusted vertically. You have on the right the option to auto-update
      changes you do with the controls or do it manually with the update button.
      Warning: There are some disabled controls.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>FFPlayer</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="../images/ags_ffplayer.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<para>
	  The ffplayer screenshot
	</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Produce audio data by opening Soundfont2 audio file container format. There three available
      controls, preset and instrument to navigate within container format and a open button to
      read Soundfont2 files and assign the selected instrument to the input.
    </para>
    <para>
      The ffplayer contains recently the bridge widget. You can add plugins in bulk mode by
      click Add or Remove within AgsFFPlayer's bridge, what you can collapse/expand. To add an effect
      to a line, you have open as usual input/output of machine properties.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
