<?xml version='1.0' encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY ags "Advanced Gtk+ Sequencer">
]>

<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 -->
<!-- or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; -->
<!-- with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. -->
<!-- A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU -->
<!-- Free Documentation License". -->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>The menubar</title>
  <para>
    Within the menubar you may do basic tasks like open/close files. In this section we cover
    briefly the the different entries. The menus have mnemonics e.g. press ALT and F key in order
    to open File menu.
  </para>

  <sect1>
    <title>File</title>
    <para>
      The file menu lets you do maintenance related to files or quit application. Note there was a simple
      XML file format introduced in 0.7.x to speed up things. The advanced file format needs optimization
      work to fulfill. The file format can be modified by configuration file located in your home directory
      $(HOME)/.gsequencer/ags.conf. The simple file interface is defaulted and can be altered by section
      generic and simple-file key set to false.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Open - open an &ags; XML file. Uses per configuration the simple XML Input/Ouput interface.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Save - save your current work. Uses per configuration the simple XML Input/Ouput interface.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Save as - save your current work as a different filename. Uses per configuration the simple
	  XML Input/Ouput interface.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Export - export to PCM audio file.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Quit - leave &ags;.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Export to PCM audio file</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_export_window.png" />
	</imageobject>
	<caption>
	  <para>
	    The export window screenshot
	  </para>
	</caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>
	This shows you the export dialog. Exclude sequencers affect mainly AgsDrum and AgsMatrix pattern sequencers
	to be started to output. You may select filename to export to and duration of the exported track. BPM adjustment
	is take from the navigation. Basically &ags; exports what you hear of the speakers.
      </para>
      <para>
	With the export toggle button you can start exporting to PCM audio file or stop it at an arbitrary time.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Edit</title>
    <para>
      The edit menu lets you add audio machines of the related submenu, open automation window or preferences dialog.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Add - select of different machines. You might want to add the bridged machines of plugins like LADSPA, DSSI or
	  Lv2. Instrument plugins are available within notation editor.
	</para>

	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Panel - acts as your default sink.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Mixer - enables you to bundle your different output engines.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Drum - is used to do pattern editing using PCM audio files. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Matrix - is used to pattern editing, intended to be linked against Synth.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Synth - is a software synthesizer supporting variable oscillator count.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      FFPlayer - may be used to open Soundfont2 audio file container format in order to do
	      notation.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Preferences - open preferences dialog.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <sect2>
      <title>Preferences dialog</title>
      <para>
	Within preferences dialog you may choose between different topics. For each one one tab. The configuration
	is applied in place after click Apply or OK. There is no need to restart the application.
      </para>

      <sect3>
	<title>Generic</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_generic_preferences.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The preferences dialog screenshot - generic tab
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>

	<para>
	  The autosave thread option enables auto-saving to $HOME/.gsequencer directory. Segmentation is
	  used as a delay factor, you can do tactation with it.
	</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
	<title>Audio</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_audio_preferences.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The preferences dialog screenshot - audio tab
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
	  Sound card is your physical devices to do playback.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Audio channels specifies the audio channels to allocate for output device.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Samplerate affects the entire project. Your audio files have to be at very same rate further
	  your device has to support the given rate. Like buffer size this affects the thread's related to
	  audio processing their frequencies. Note a too low frequency may cause unexpected behavior like
	  no proper velocity.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Buffer size is used for all audio buffers. Your soundcard has to support the passed buffer size.
	  This preference affects thread's frequencies.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Format determines the storage size of one frame. All available formats are signed integers. The
	  following sizes in bits are available: 8, 16, 24, 32 and 64. Your hardware has a need to support
	  the format in order to get sounds.
	</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
	<title>Performance</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="../images/ags_performance_preferences.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>
	      The preferences dialog screenshot - performance tab
	    </para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
	  Auto-sense on stream is required for certain plugins and recalls but may cause additional performance
	  losses.
	</para>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
