<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY libagsthreadso "libags_thread.so.1">
<!ENTITY libagsaudioso "libags_audio.so.1">
<!ENTITY libagsso "libags.so.1">
<!ENTITY chap3 "chapter 3">
]>

<!-- Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document -->
<!-- under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 -->
<!-- or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; -->
<!-- with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. -->
<!-- A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU -->
<!-- Free Documentation License". -->

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0">
  <title>The application context</title>
  <para>
    Making Advanced Gtk+ Sequencer objects reachable from different contices was
    mandatory as introducing AgsApplicationContext. Imagine you are within a GUI
    callback and want to lookup a soundcard or sequencer the application context
    shall provide this functioanlity and provide access to its objects through a
    well defined interface. As doing it with interfaces you are not limited to one
    specific implementation rather having the option to choose the appropriate one
    implementing the interfaces.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are different contices available e.g. AgsThreadApplicationContext providing
    its functionality by AgsConcurrencyProvider, AgsAudioApplicationContext giving
    you the wished objects by implementing AgsConcurrencyProvider and AgsSoundProvider.
    For example the code below should each giving you the same meaning object but
    using different contices.
  </para>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Implementations and their interfaces</title>
    <para>
      Creating a AgsThreadApplicationContext and then get the task thread by calling
      <code language="C">AgsThread* ags_concurrency_provider_get_task_thread(AgsConcurrencyProvider*)</code>.
      Since the AgsConcurrency interface is implemented by the context, we retrieve
      the task thread. The AgsTaskThread gives you a thread safe signal. It is used
      to launch AgsTask objects to do thread safe operations but later on this.
    </para>
    
    <example>
      <title>Thread application context</title>
      <programlisting language="C">
<xi:include href="../listings/thread_application_context.c" parse="text" />
      </programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>
      The AgsAudioApplicationContext inherites from AgsApplicationContext and implements
      the AgsConcurrency interface, too. So you can retrieve the task thread the same
      way. But the context implements one more, the AgsSoundProvider interface. Giving
      you objects related to threading and audio processing.
    </para>
    
    <example>
      <title>Audio application context</title>
      <programlisting language="C">
<xi:include href="../listings/audio_application_context.c" parse="text" />
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>The main loop property</title>
    <para>
      AgsApplicationContext:main-loop does usually point to an AgsThread implementing
      AgsMainLoop interface. &libagsthreadso; provides you the AgsGenericMainLoop object or
      if you intend to use &libagsaudioso;, this property shall point to AgsAudioLoop.
    </para>

    <sect2>
      <title>AgsMainLoop interface</title>
      <para>
	As it shall be implemented by AGS_TYPE_THREAD subtypes, this parent object provides
	a mutex to properly lock the object. You should obtain the pthread_mutex_t pointer
	by calling <code language="C">pthread_mutex_t* ags_mutex_manager_lookup(AgsMutexManager*, GObject*)</code>.
      </para>

      <para>
	The main loop specifies some signals like ::interrupt, ::monitor and ::change-frequency.
	They are all related to realtime behavior of an application. Assumed you have a thread
	you want to run within the thread tree, but it is not mandatory to run it. With these
	functions you can determine if you shall pause your thread during ::interrupt signal.
	How many time you are allowed to consume or running at all, can be concluded by using
	::monitor. In order to get notified about modified refreshing rate of your thread, listen
	to ::change-frequency signal.
      </para>

      <para>
	The interface provides some other function pointers. If you want to provide AgsTaskThread
	to your application, use <code language="C">void ags_main_loop_set_async_queue(AgsMainLoop*, GObject*)</code>
	and <code language="C">GObject* ags_main_loop_get_async_queue(AgsMainLoop*)</code>.
      </para>

      <para>
	To control the AgsThread::clock signal AgsMainLoop's methods are going to be invoked.
	The involved functions are:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <code language="C">void ags_main_loop_set_tic(AgsMainLoop*, guint)</code>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <code language="C">guint ags_main_loop_get_tic(AgsMainLoop*)</code>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <code language="C">void ags_main_loop_set_last_sync(AgsMainLoop*, guint)</code>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <code language="C">guint ags_main_loop_get_last_sync(AgsMainLoop*)</code>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>The config property</title>
    <para>
      The AgsApplicationContext base class provides you an AgsConfig instance. It might
      load a default configuration or from current users home directory. The config should
      be obtained as property using <code language="C">void g_object_get(gpointer, gchar*, ...)</code>
      or similar.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      AgsConfig stores its properties as key value pairs within appropriate group. In order
      to get the config instance, load default configuration and get the threading model do
      the following.
    </para>
    
    <example>
      <title>Get config value</title>
      <programlisting language="C">
<xi:include href="../listings/config.c" parse="text" />
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>The file property</title>
    <para>
      You might want to set an AgsFile or AgsSimpleFile instance within your application context. This in
      view of having your application persisted.
    </para>

    <example>
      <title>The application context :file property</title>
      <programlisting language="C">
<xi:include href="../listings/file_property.c" parse="text" />
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>The application mutex</title>
    <para>
      The probably most important property is :application-mutex. You should get it and copy
      to your very own toplevel object. Since all access to AgsApplicationContext should be
      protected by the mutex of concurrent access. This property is provided by AgsMutexManager,
      too.
    </para>

    <example>
      <title>The application mutex</title>
      <programlisting language="C">
<xi:include href="../listings/application_mutex.c" parse="text" />
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Program start and termination</title>
    <para>
      The application context provides signals to make your application ready to run. You
      basically implement AgsApplicationContext::prepare, AgsApplicationContext::setup and
      AgsApplicationContext::register-types. It is upto you how the application shall behave.
    </para>

    <para>
      AgsApplicationContext::quit signal terminates your application. Feel free to provide your
      own implementation.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Abstract data connection</title>
    <para>
      AgsDataConnectionManager is a singleton you can retrieve its instance by calling
      <code language="C">AgsConnectionManager* ags_connection_manager_get_instance()</code>.
      It usually provides AGS_TYPE_CONNECTION subtypes, like AgsAudioConnection which does
      provide about assigned soundcard and its channel mapping.
    </para>

    <para>
      AgsConnection contains one single property :data-object. As you provide a message queue
      consuming &libagsso;, you can retrieve modifications asynchronously. How the message
      queue is polled is explained in &chap3;.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Common interfaces</title>
    <para>
      Use AgsConnectable or AgsDynamicConnectable if you intend to listen to a particular
      event. If you want to connect an event of an object known during instantiation time
      use ::connect and ::disconnect. Assumed the object needs to be resolved, you can
      ::connect-dynamic ::disconnect-dynamic, later.
    </para>

    <para>
      AgsPlugin interface provides persistence to a well known abstract base type. Since it
      has various implementations, this interface provides <code language="C">void ags_plugin_read(AgsFile*, xmlNode*, AgsPlugin*)</code>
      and <code language="C">xmlNode* ags_plugin_write(AgsFile*, xmlNode*, AgsPlugin*)</code>
    </para>

    <para>
      Likewise there are the interfaces intended to use with sound related objects AgsSoundcard,
      AgsSequencer, AgsMutable and AgsSeekable.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
