<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0">
  <title>The recycling tree</title>
  <para>
    AgsRecycling has a strong relation to AgsChannel although not every channel might
    have its very own recycling. Rather having a reference to a start and end region
    of an inter-connnected AgsRecycling. It may create or destroy audio signals event
    based.
  </para>

  <para>
    Inter-connected gets its meaning as ags_channel_set_recycling() invoked by
    ags_channel_set_link() connects AgsRecycling:next and AgsRecycling:prev together
    from different channels. Providing you the AgsRecyclingContext. A recycling context
    has generally one parent and many children from different channels.
  </para>

  <para>
    AgsRecallID points to one recycling context in order to make decisions of what
    level you are running in. Theoretically super-threaded tree can run upto the
    recycling context level.
  </para>

  <para>
    Note, recyclings have they own recall base object AgsRecallRecycling. Usually, you
    do ags_recall_add_child() to instances inherit of AgsRecallChannelRun.
  </para>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Add and remove audio signal</title>
    <para>
      The two signals ::add_audio_signal and ::remove_audio_signal should be invoked
      as adding or removing AgsAudioSignal to an AgsRecycling. Recalls act as producer
      or consumer of AgsAudioSignal. They do basically play notation or process your
      effects. Its are located in AgsAudio or AgsChannel.
    </para>

    <para>
      There is generally a need for providing a template audio signal within your recycling.
      As this does this example. This reduces the overhead of reading files for every
      playing during a button click, notation or pattern.
    </para>

    <example>
      <title>AgsRecycling and AgsAudioSignal</title>
      <programlisting language="C">
<xi:include href="../listings/recycling.c" parse="text" />
      </programlisting>
    </example>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
